Finding Aid for Philip Newell Youtz papers, 1920-1972
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Philip Newell Youtz papers 1920-1972
Youtz, Philip Newell, 1895-1972.
86386 Aa 2
Architect, inventor and educator, director of the Brooklyn Museum, and dean of the College of Architecture and Design of the University of Michigan. Notebooks, articles and reports relating to his work as museum director in Brooklyn, New York, and at the Pennsylvania Museum of Art, articles and notebooks, 1922-1924, concerning his work as Home Secretary of the Canton Christian College, Canton, China, and other materials relating to his work with the War Production Board during World War II, his architectural projects and inventions; and photographs.
3 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Frances Youtz (donor no. 5240 ).
Periodic additions to the records are not expected.
The collection is open to research.
Philip N. Youtz was born April 27, 1895 in Quincy, Massachusetts. He was educated at Amherst College (1918) and Oberlin College (1919). During the period 1920-1922, he built schools and a non-sectarian Chinese Christian College in Canton, China. Upon his return, he did publicity work in New York City for the College while also teaching at Teachers College, Columbia University. He also taught extension courses in philosophy and logic at Columbia, and supervised art courses at the People's Institute.
After receiving his architectural degree from Columbia University in 1929, he became curator of the Sixty-Ninth St. branch of the Pennsylvania Museum of Art in Philadelphia. In 1933 he became assistant director of the Brooklyn Museum of Art and served as director from 1934 to 1938. From 1938 to 1940, he was director of Pacific House at the Golden Gate International Exposition and the Pacific Area in San Francisco. Following the war where he served with the War Production Board, Youtz was a practicing architect in the New York City area. Here he invented the "lift slab" method of construction in which concrete slabs are raised on supporting columns to form different stories of a building. He came to the University of Michigan in 1957, where he was soon named dean of the College of Architecture and Design, a post he held until his retirement in 1964.
Youtz was a member of the Engineering Society of Detroit, the New York Historical Society, the American Association of Museums and the Association of Collegiate Schools of Architecture. He was a director of the Detroit Chapter of the American Institute of Architects, the Michigan Association of the Professions and the Ann Arbor Art Association.
Youtz died in January 1972.
The Youtz papers consist of notebooks, articles and reports relating to his work as museum director in Brooklyn, New York, and at the Pennsylvania Museum of Art, articles and notebooks, 1922-1924, concerning his work as Home Secretary of the Canton Christian College, Canton, China. Other papers include materials relating to his work with the War Production Board during World War II, his architectural projects and inventions, and photographs. The papers are arranged into three series: Biographical/Personal; Career Materials; and Published Materials.
Subjects:
Architects.; Architecture.; Brooklyn Museum.; Guangzhou (China); Canton Christian College.; China--History--Republic, 1912-1949.; Inventions.; Pennsylvania Museum of Art.; United States. War Production Board.; University of Michigan. College of Architecture and Design.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; World War, 1939-1945.; Youtz, Frances May Leffler, 1897-1975.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Architecture.; Brooklyn Museum.; Buddhist temples.; China--History--Republic, 1912-1949.; Inventions.; Religious articles.; Youtz, Philip Newell, 1895-1972.
Genre Terms:
Albums.; Photographs.
- Biographical/Personal
  - Biographical information and description of the Youtz collection prepared by Mrs. Frances Youtz 1972 (Box 1)
  - Photographic album, "Architectural Design" (Box 1)
  - Photographic album, "Science of Construction" (Box 1)
  - Photographs: portraits and informal photographs from their service in China (Box 1)
  - Unpublished articles (Box 1)
  - Published articles and reviews (Box 1)
  - Speeches and articles (Box 1)
  - Franklin Institute of the State of Pennsylvania for the Promotion of the Mechanic award 1968 (Box 1)
    (Frank P. Brown Medal for 1968)
  - Paper prepared for the International Museums Office of the International Institute of Intellectual Cooperation of the League of Nations for a Conference in Madrid in October 1934 (Box 1)
  - US Capitol Building 1958 (Box 1)
    (includes letter from Harry S. Truman)
  - Architectural Awards of Excellence 1963 (Box 1)
    (Youtz was judge)
- Career Materials
  - Canton Christian College, Canton, China
    - Correspondence to family and friends
      - January-June 1920 (Box 1)
      - July-December 1920 (Box 1)
      - 1921-1922 (Box 1)
    - Printed material (Box 1)
    - College publicity 1924-1925 (Box 1)
  - People's Institute, New York
    - Printed Material 1927-1929 (Box 1)
  - Pennsylvania Museum of Art
    - Scrapbook 1931-1933 (Box 1)
    - Notebook of articles relating to the Museum 1931-1932 (Box 1)
    - Report of survey made for the 69th Street branch of the Museum 1931 (Box 1)
    - Report of the 69th Street branch of the Museum 1931 (Box 1)
  - Brooklyn Museum 1933-1938
    - Photograph album (Box 2)
    - Printed Material (Box 2)
  - Pacific House (theme building of the Golden Gate International Exposition and the Pacific Area) 1938-1940
    - Notebook containing description of exhibits, photograph, essay, reports, etc. 1939 (Box 2)
    - Volume: entitled Pacific House in & out by Antonio Sotomayor and containing original water color drawings parodying the people and work of Pacific House (Box 2)
    - Printed material: include bibliographies and articles (Box 2)
  - War Production Board and Smaller War Plants Corporation
    - Reports 1944-1945 (Box 2)
  - Yorktown Heights
    - T-Span Loading Test, engineering data 1953 (Box 2)
- Published Materials: Books written by, edited, or with a contribution by, PNY
  - The New Arts series (Box 2)
    (5 volumes edited by Youtz)
  - An Outline of Aesthetics series (Box 2)
    (5 volumes edited with introductory notes by Youtz)
  - American Life in Architecture (Box 3)
  - Sounding Stones of Architecture (Box 3)
  - Prose Patterns (Box 3)
  - Home Making as a Center for Research (report of the Teachers College Conferences on Homemaking) (Box 3)
  - Classics of the Western World (Box 3)
  - Early American Rooms edited by Russell Hawes Kettell (Box 3)